<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Sri Guru Granth Sahib Ji Quotes</string>
    <string name="tab_Final_Quote">Quote</string>
    <string name="tab_text_1">The Khalsa belongs to God; all victory is the victory of God.</string>
    <string name="tab_text_2">ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਕਾ ਖ਼ਾਲਸਾ, ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਕੀ ਫਤਹਿ।</string>
    <string name="message_quote">Get Quote</string>
    <string name="message_hukamnama">Hukamnama</string>
    <string name="message_ardaas">Ardaas</string>
    <string name="message_nitnem">Nitnem</string>
    <string name="message_sangat">Sangat</string>
    <string name="message_calendar">Calendar</string>
    <string name="title_activity_ardaas">Ardaas</string>
    <string name="large_text1">"Coming Soon"</string>
    <string name="large_text2">
        "Introduction:
‘Nit’ means daily, regularly or always. ‘Nem’ is the Punjabi form of ‘Neeam’ meaning law, rule or practice. ‘Nitnem’ thus means ‘daily practice’.

Nit Nem is a collaboration of different banis that were designated to be read by sikhs every day - the banis to be read has been prescribed in the Panthic Sikh Reht Maryada, (the Sikh Code of Conduct).

The Nit Nem bani's usually include the Panj bania which are read in the morning between 3:00 am and 6:00 am (this period is considered as Amrit Vela or the Ambrosial Hours) and Rehras Sahib in the evening 6pm and Kirtan Sohila at night before sleeping. The morning Nitnem was corrected to include all 5 Banian; Japji Sahib, Jaap Sahib, Svaiyye, Chaupai Sahib and Anand Sahib.

Morning Nitnem:
Japji Sahib - is the first sacred composition found in the Guru Granth Sahib. It is a famous and concise summary of Sikh philosophy which was compiled by Guru Nanak Dev Ji. The compilation consists of the Mool Mantar, an opening Salok or verse, a set of 38 Pauris and a final closing Salok. This Bani called Japji Sahib, appears at the very beginning of the Guru Granth Sahib. The word Jap means to recite/to chant. Ji is a word that is used to show respect as is the word ‘Sahib’.

Jaap Sahib - is the bani uttered by Guru Gobind Singh Ji. It is the second bani of the five in the daily morning prayer routine of a Sikh. Jaap Sahib is made up of 199 verses and is the first Bani of Sri Dasam Granth Sahib Ji. The language of Jaap has words and compounds drawn from Sanskrit, Brij Bhasha, Arabic and Persian.

Tav Prasad Swayae - is bani composed by Guru Gobind Singh which tells us how to worship and realise God. This Bani appears in Sri Dasam Granth Sahib Ji. Historical accounts says that this bani was composed for Raja Bhim Chand when Guru ji was in Paunta Sahib to show him that by having thousands of forces or infinite land or kingdoms, one cannot attain God.

Kabiobach Benti Chaupai - is bani composed by Guru Gobind Singh and appears in Sri Dasam Granth Sahib Ji. The Bani offers protection and security and many Sikhs recite this bani to gain spiritual safety and defence from external and internal enemies, worries and afflictions. The Gurmukhi text is simple yet very powerful and gives one self confidence and an upbeat feeling. This bani gives one the feeling of reliability and dependability on the Lord. If one has negative feelings and a lack of confidence in the future, one should recite this bani to get an instant boost.

Anand Sahib - is bani that was written by Guru Amar Das Ji and appears in Sri Guru Granth Sahib Ji. It is said that the person who recites this Holy Bani daily with dedication, attention and comprehension, will achieve Anand (Complete Happiness or Bliss) in life.

Evening Nitnem:
Rehiras Sahib - is the evening prayer of the Sikhs, which speaks of the greatness of Waheguru. As recorded in the Guru Granth Sahib Ji, it contains the hymns of five different Gurus; Guru Nanak Dev Ji, Guru Amar Das Ji, Guru Ram Das Ji, Guru Arjan Dev Ji and Guru Gobind Singh Ji. Each section of the prayer casts light on another aspect of God. It is recited after a hard days work when one is tired. It adds energy to both the body and the mind allowing one to conclude their day, giving thanks to the Almighty for the completion of another successful day.

Night Nitnem:
Kirtan Sohila - is the night time prayer said by all Sikhs before they go to sleep. The first three shabads were uttered by Guru Nanak Dev Ji, the fourth shabad by Guru Ram Das Ji and the fifth shabad by Guru Arjan Dev. This bani describes the pain of separation and celebrating the bliss of union.
        "</string>
    <string name="large_text">
        "
Resources used:
https://nitnempath.com/ardas-english-translation/
https://wahegurunet.com/ardaas/

Introduction to Ardaas:
-Ardaas is a Sikh prayer before God.
-The word Ardaas is derived from the Persian word ‘Arazdashat’, meaning a request, a supplication, a prayer, a petition or an address to a superior authority.

It is done in one of the following situations:
-Before performing or after undertaking any significant task
-After reciting the daily Sikh prayers (Bani)
-After the completion of a service such as hymn-singing (Kirtan).

        Ardaas
ੴ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਕੀ ਫ਼ਤਹਿ॥
Ek-Oankar. Waheguroo Ji Ki Fateh
God is One. All victory is of the Wondrous Guru (God).

ਸ੍ਰੀ ਭਗੌਤੀ ਜੀ ਸਹਾਇ॥
Sri Bhagouti ji Sahai
May the respected sword (God in the form of the Destroyer of evil doers) help us!

ਵਾਰ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਭਗੌਤੀ ਜੀ ਕੀ ਪਾਤਸ਼ਾਹੀ 10॥
Vaar Sri Bhagouti Ji Ki Paatshaahee Dasvee
Ode of the respected sword recited by the Tenth Guru.

ਪ੍ਰਿਥਮ ਭਗੌਤੀ ਸਿਮਰਿ ਕੈ ਗੁਰ ਨਾਨਕ ਲਈਂ ਧਿਆਇ॥
Pritham Bhagouti Simar Kai, Guru Naanak Layee Dhiyae
First remember the sword (God in the form of Destroyer of evil doers); then remember and meditate upon Guru Nanak.

ਫਿਰ ਅੰਗਦ ਗੁਰ ਤੇ ਅਮਰਦਾਸੁ ਰਾਮਦਾਸੈ ਹੋਈਂ ਸਹਾਇ॥
Angad Gur Te Amar Das, Raamdaasai Hoye Sahai
Then remember and meditate upon Guru Angad, Guru Amar Das and Guru Ram Das: May they help us!

ਅਰਜਨ ਹਰਗੋਬਿੰਦ ਨੋ ਸਿਮਰੌ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਹਰਿਰਾਇ॥
Arjan Hargobind No Simrou Sri Har Rai
Remember and meditate upon Guru Arjan, Guru Hargobind and Respected Guru Har Rai.

ਸ੍ਰੀ ਹਰਿਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨ ਧਿਆਇਐ ਜਿਸ ਡਿਠੈ ਸਭਿ ਦੁਖ ਜਾਇ॥
Sri HarKrishan Dhiyaa-eeai Jis Dhithi Sabh Dukh Jaye
Remember and meditate upon respected Guru Har Krishan, by having the sight of whom, all pains vanish.

ਤੇਗ ਬਹਾਦਰ ਸਿਮਰਿਐ ਘਰ ਨਉ ਨਿਧਿ ਆਵੈ ਧਾਇ॥
Teg Bahadur Simareeai Ghar No Nidh Avai Dhai
Remember and meditate upon Guru Tegh Bahadur; and then nine sources of wealth will come hastening to your home.

ਸਭ ਥਾਂਈ ਹੋਇ ਸਹਾਇ॥
Sabh Thai Ho-e Sahaai
Oh Respected Gurus! kindly help us everywhere. (*This is the end of the section written by Guru Gobind Singh ji, the rest was compiled after the Guru’s time.)

ਦਸਵਾਂ ਪਾਤਸ਼ਾਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗੋਬਿੰਦ ਸਿੰਘ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ! ਸਭ ਥਾਂਈ ਹੋਇ ਸਹਾਇ॥
Dasvaa Paatshaah Guru Gobind Singh Ji Sabh Thai Ho-e Sahaai
May the kind, the respected Tenth Guru Gobind Singh assist us everywhere.

ਦਸਾਂ ਪਾਤਸ਼ਾਹੀਆਂ ਦੀ ਜੋਤ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪਾਠ ਦੀਦਾਰ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰ ਕੇ ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।।
Dasa Paatsaaheea Di Jot Sri Guru Granth Sahib Ji, De Paath Deedaar Daa Dhiyaan Dhar Ke Bolo Ji Waheguroo
Think and meditate upon the divine light of the Ten Kings contained in the respected Guru Granth Sahib and turn your thoughts to the divine teachings of and get pleasure by the sight of Guru Granth Sahib; Utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਪੰਜਾਂ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ,ਚੌਹਾਂ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ, ਚਾਲ੍ਹੀਆਂ ਮੁਕਤਿਆਂ, ਹਠੀਆਂ ਜਪੀਆਂ, ਤਪੀਆਂ,
ਜਿਹਨਾਂ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਿਆ, ਵੰਡ ਛਕਿਆ, ਦੇਗ ਚਲਾਈ, ਤੇਗ ਵਾਹੀ, ਦੇਖ ਕੇ ਅਣਡਿੱਠ ਕੀਤਾ,
ਤਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ, ਸਚਿਆਰਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਕਮਾਈ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰ ਕੇ, ਖਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ ! ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।।
Panja Piyariya, Chauhaa Sahibzadiya, Chaliya Mukhtiya, Huthiya, Jupiya, Tupiya, Jina Nam Jupiya, Vand Shakiya, Deg Chalaaee, Teg Vaahee, Dekh Ke Andhith Keetaa, Tinhaa Piariyaa, Sachiaariyaa Dee Kamaaee, Da Dhiyaan Dhar Ke Bolo Ji Waheguroo
Think of the deeds of the Five Beloved Ones, of the four sons (of Guru Gobind Singh); of the Forty Martyrs; of the brave Sikhs of indomitable determination; of the devotees steeped in the colour of the Name; of those who were absorbed in the Name; of those who remembered the Name and shared their food in companionship; of those who started free kitchens; of those who wielded their swords (for preserving truth); of those who overlooked others shortcomings; All the aforesaid were pure and truly devoted ones; Utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਿੰਘਾਂ ਸਿੰਘਣੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਧਰਮ ਹੇਤ ਸੀਸ ਦਿੱਤੇ, ਬੰਦ ਬੰਦ ਕਟਾਏ, ਖੋਪਰੀਆਂ ਲੁਹਾਈਆਂ,
ਚਰਖੀਆਂ ਤੇ ਚੜੇ, ਆਰਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਚਿਰਾਏ ਗਏ, ਗੁਰਦਵਾਰਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਲਈ ਕੁਰਬਾਨੀਆਂ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ,
ਧਰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਹਾਰਿਆ, ਸਿੱਖੀ ਕੇਸਾਂ ਸੁਆਸਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਨਿਬਾਹੀ, ਤਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਕਮਾਈ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰ ਕੇ ਖਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ।।
Jinaa Singhaa Singhneeyaa Ne Dharam Het Sees Dithe, Bund Bund Kuttai, Khopriya Luhayiya, Charukriya Te Churhe, Aariaa Naal Chiraae Ge, Gurdwaraiya Di Seva Layee Kurbaniya Keethiya, Dharam Nehee Haariye, Sikhi Kesaa Suwaasaa Naal Nibaahee, Tina Dee Kamaaee Daa Dhiyaan Dhar Ke Bolo Ji Waheguroo
Think of and remember the unique service rendered by those brave Sikh men as well as women, who sacrificed their heads but did not surrender their Sikh Religion; Who got themselves cut to pieces from each of the joints of the body; Who got their scalps removed; Who were tied and rotated on the wheels and broken into pieces; Who were cut by saws; Who were flayed alive; Who sacrificed themselves to upkeep the dignity of the Gurdwaras; Who did not abandon their Sikh faith; Who kept their Sikh Religion and saved their long hair till their last breath; Utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ! ਪੰਜਾਂ ਤਖਤਾਂ, ਸਰਬੱਤ ਗੁਰਦੁਆਰਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰ ਕੇ ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।।
[Bolo Ji Waheguroo! Panja] Takhta, Sarbat Gurdwariya Daa Dhiyaan Dhur Ke Bolo Ji Waheguroo
Turn your thoughts to all of the seats of Sikh Religion and all the Gurdwaras; utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਪ੍ਰਿਥਮੇ ਸਰਬੱਤ ਖਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ ਕੀ ਅਰਦਾਸ ਹੈ ਜੀ, ਸਰਬੱਤ ਖਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ ਕੋ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ, ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ, ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਚਿਤ ਆਵੇ,
ਚਿੱਤ ਆਵਨ ਕਾ ਸਦਕਾ ਸਰਬ ਸੁਖ ਹੋਵੇ। ਜਹਾਂ ਜਹਾਂ ਖਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ ਸਾਹਿਬ, ਤਹਾਂ ਤਹਾਂ ਰਛਿਆ ਰਿਆਇਤ, ਦੇਗ ਤੇਗ ਫ਼ਤਹ,
ਬਿਰਦ ਕੀ ਪੈਜ, ਪੰਥ ਕੀ ਜੀਤ, ਸ੍ਰੀ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਸਹਾਇ, ਖਾਲਸੇ ਜੀ ਕੇ ਬੋਲ ਬਾਲੇ, ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।।
Prithme Sarbat Khaalsaa Ji Ki Ardaas Hai Ji, Sarbat Khaalsaa Ji Ko Waheguroo Waheguroo Waheguroo Chit Aavai Chit Aavan Ka Sadkaa Surab Sukh Hovai
Jahaa Jahaa Khaalsaa Ji Saahib, Tahaa Tahaa Ruchhiya Riyaa-it, Deg Teg Fateh, Bira Ki Paij, Panth Ki Jeet, Sree Saahib Ji Sahaai Khaalse Ji Ko Bol Baaley, Bolo Ji Waheguroo
First the entire respected Khalsa make this supplication that may they meditate on Your Name; and may all pleasures and comforts come through such meditation.
Wherever respected Khalsa is present, give Your protection and grace; May the free kitchen and sword never fail; Maintain the honour of your devotees; Confer victory upon the Sikh people; May the respected sword always come to our assistance; May the Khalsa always get honours; Utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਿੱਖੀ ਦਾਨ, ਕੇਸ ਦਾਨ, ਰਹਿਤ ਦਾਨ, ਬਿਬੇਕ ਦਾਨ, ਵਿਸਾਹ ਦਾਨ, ਭਰੋਸਾ ਦਾਨ, ਦਾਨਾਂ ਸਿਰ ਦਾਨ,
ਨਾਮ ਦਾਨ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤਸਰ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ, ਚੌਕੀਆਂ, ਝੰਡੇ, ਬੁੰਗੇ, ਜੁਗੋ ਜੁਗ ਅਟੱਲ, ਧਰਮ ਕਾ ਜੈਕਾਰ, ਬੋਲੋ ਜੀ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।।
Sikhaa Noo Sikhee Daan, Kesh Daan, Rehit Daan, Bibek Daan, Bharosaa Daan, Daanaa Sir Daan Naam Daan, Chounkiyaa Jhande Bunge Jugo Jug Attal, Dharam Ka Jai Kaar Bolo Ji Waheguroo
Kindly confer upon the Sikhs the gift of Sikhism, the gift of long hair, the gift of observing Sikh laws, the gift of divine knowledge, the gift of firm faith, the gift of belief and the biggest gift of Name. O God! May the choirs, the mansion and the banners exist forever; may the truth ever triumph; utter Wahe Guru (Wondrous God)!

ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਨੀਵਾਂ, ਮਤ ਉੱਚੀ ਮਤ ਦਾ ਰਾਖਾ ਆਪਿ ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ।
Sikhaa Daa Man Neevaa, Mat Uchee, Mat Pat Daa Raakhaa Aap Waheguroo
May the minds of all the Sikhs remain humble and their wisdom exalted; O God! You are the protector of wisdom.

ਹੇ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਆਪਣੇ ਪੰਥ ਦੇ ਸਦਾ ਸਹਾਈ ਦਾਤਾਰ ਜੀਓ।।
Hae [Akal Purakh Aapne Panth De Sada Suhai Datar Jio]
[*O Akal Purakh, live as the ever helpful giver of your Panth?]

ਸ੍ਰੀ ਨਨਕਾਣਾ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਗੁਰਦੁਆਰਿਆਂ ਗੁਰਧਾਮਾਂ ਦੇ,
ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪੰਥ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਛੋੜਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ, ਖੁਲ੍ਹੇ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੀਦਾਰ ਤੇ ਸੇਵਾ ਸੰਭਾਲ ਦਾ ਦਾਨ ਖ਼ਾਲਸਾ ਜੀ ਨੂੰ ਬਖਸ਼ੋ।
ਹੇ ਨਿਮਾਣਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਮਾਣ, ਨਿਤਾਣਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਤਾਣ, ਨਿਓਟਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਓਟ, ਸੱਚੇ ਪਿਤਾ, ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ! ਆਪ ਦੇ ਹਜ਼ੂਰ…..ਦੀ ਅਰਦਾਸ ਹੈ ਜੀ।
Nimaneeaa De Maan, Nitaneeaa De Taan, Nioteeaa Di Ot, Sachey Pita Waheguroo (Aap Di Hazoor…)
O True Father, Wahe Guru! you are the honour of the meek, the Power of the helpless ones, the shelter of the shelterless, we humbly make prayer in your presence…..(substitute the occasion or prayer made here).

ਅੱਖਰ ਵਾਧਾ ਘਾਟਾ ਭੁੱਲ ਚੁੱਕ ਮਾਫ ਕਰਨੀ।
ਸਰਬੱਤ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਜ ਰਾਸ ਕਰਨੇ।
Akhar Vaadhaa Ghaataa Bhul Chuk Maaf Karnee, Sarbat De Kaaraj Raas Karney.
Kindly pardon our errors and shortcomings in reciting the above Prayer. Kindly fulfill the objects of all.

ਸੇਈ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਮੇਲ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਿਲਿਆਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਚਿਤ ਆਵੇ।
[Saei piaare mel jina miliaa tera nam vit aavae]

ਨਾਨਕ ਨਾਮ ਚੜ੍ਹਦੀ ਕਲਾ, ਤੇਰੇ ਭਾਣੇ ਸਰਬੱਤ ਦਾ ਭਲਾ।
[Nanak nam chardi kala, tere parne sarbat di pala]

ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਕਾ ਖ਼ਾਲਸਾ, ਵਾਹਿਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਕੀ ਫਤਹਿ।।
Waheguroo Ji Ka Khaalsaa Waheguroo Ji Ki Fateh
The Khalsa belongs to God; all victory is the victory of God."
    </string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_hukamnama">Hukamnama</string>
    <string name="title_activity_nitnem">Nitnem</string>
    <string name="appwidget_text">EXAMPLE</string>
    <string name="add_widget">Add widget</string>
    <string name="title_activity_sangat">Sangat</string>
    <string name="prompt_email">Email</string>
    <string name="prompt_password">Password</string>
    <string name="action_sign_in">Sign in or register</string>
    <string name="action_sign_in_short">Sign in</string>
    <string name="welcome">"Welcome !"</string>
    <string name="invalid_username">Not a valid username</string>
    <string name="invalid_password">Password must be >5 characters</string>
    <string name="login_failed">"Login failed"</string>
    <string name="title_activity_settings">Settings</string>

    <!-- Preference Titles -->
    <string name="messages_header">Messages</string>
    <string name="sync_header">Sync</string>

    <!-- Messages Preferences -->
    <string name="signature_title">Your signature</string>
    <string name="reply_title">Default reply action</string>

    <!-- Sync Preferences -->
    <string name="sync_title">Sync email periodically</string>
    <string name="attachment_title">Download incoming attachments</string>
    <string name="attachment_summary_on">Automatically download attachments for incoming emails
    </string>
    <string name="attachment_summary_off">Only download attachments when manually requested</string>
</resources>